good morning welcome to meditating with
Chandra Vicki I'm a psychologist and
cognitive scientists at the University
of Cairo academically scientifically
study phenomena like mindfulness and
related phenomena like insight low
mystical experience transformative
experience higher states of
consciousness cultivation of wisdom
realization of enlightenment welcome
I've also been practicing the pasta
meditation meta contemplation Tai Chi
Chuan and chicon for over 29 years and
teaching them for close to 20 years this
itself is a course every Monday
yesterday for example there's a Dharma
in which I will teach a principle a
practice a set of skills that build on
the previous ones and so if you are
drawing for the first time you're
welcome to stay but go to the
description in this video and you'll
find links to previous lessons so you
can catch off Tuesday through Friday
today's Tuesday we will sit or sometimes
review the lesson from Monday and we
will sit together at the end of every
day Monday through Friday there is a
question-and-answer please for the
question-and-answer is direct your
question and answers to the practice and
the core of this course from what before
more broadly reaching QA inviting you to
attend the live streaming Q&A we do
every Friday at 3 p.m. est on YouTube so
we've been talking about the cultivation
of integrity as the process and
integration which are situated within
the framework of for friending yourself
and so I have recommended reformulating
the trading precepts the five training
precepts as five promises promises that
you make to yourself as an active deep
defriending yourself and then I
recommended taking the negative command
structure and opening it up and do write
a more comprehensive negative and
positive promise and some of you may
recognize this is my attempt to get the
the idea of the Aristotelian golden
how we cultivate virtue properly into
the promises the idea of the practice of
integrity is we're trying to the friend
we're trying to get harmony between the
patterns and processes were trying to
inculcate in our sitting and the
patterns and processes by which we
govern who regulate and live our lives
we want that consonant we want them for
ending each other and affording each
other so that what I'm calling in my
practice will be transferred to my life
and what is occurring in my life can be
brought in to the deep meditative
reflection of I said and thereby I can
was separately open I can we I can
remember the being mode in a very deep
way and so we think of the training
precepts by setting up the process of
resonance and it also is a process by
which we are affording opportunity to
apply to apply the practices and skills
that were training in this course and
also to celebrate and to remember the
Buddha and the Dharma and the Sangha so
just to review what we do is of course
we try to live out the promises
throughout the day but at the end of our
sit right normally say now you know
slowly throughout your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you've
cultivated in your practice with the
everyday consciousness and cognition you
mind units you mindfully
recite mindfully recite those promises
to yourself with intentionality you're
trying to make a promise the way you
would make a sincere promise with
integrity let sincere promise to a
friend so you're making that promise as
a way of trying to integrate what you've
cultivated in your practice with your
everyday consciousness and cognition so
I promise not to harm but to mindfully
enhance and enrich life I promise not to
relate to material objects mindlessly
but mindfully perhaps you might want to
add remembering the being mode you can
actually add that throughout all
precepts all of these processes do you
find that helpful
anything I promise not to speak
mindlessly but mindfully I promise not
to practice sexuality mindlessly but
mindfully I promise not to cultivate
altered states of consciousness
mindlessly mindfully perhaps adding not
for escape but for the cultivation of
wisdom so we are going to go into our
sit when it comes to that point
well the timer will go off and I'll
recite what I always say coming out of
the product coming out of the sit but
then they'll be silenced for a bit
before I go into addressing some of the
Q&A in that silence you have the
opportunity if you so choose to practice
the five promises all right so please
get comfortable please make sure you set
your phones to do not disturb and we
will begin when I say begin begin
[Music]
slowly come out if you practice trying
as best you can to integrate with your
cultivated in your practice with your
everyday consciousness and cognition
pops by mine fully and intentionally
reciting the five promises to yourself
all right let's answer some questions
this is from at Miz if it's an excellent
question in this process of integrating
practice and like we thought as
analogous to platonic and agar gay
totally totally
I think that's an excellent question for
those of you I'm familiar I don't have
time to go into platonic manutaki you'll
find the discussion of this I believe in
episode 5 of leaking from the mini
crisis series and it's actually referred
to later when I talk about reciprocal
opening but I've mentioned that to all
of us when I've talked about remember in
the B mode as getting into this way
great relationship so that we get a
reciprocal opening between us in the
world and Plato high particular way of
understanding that the idea is we
achieve inner harmony and what that does
is that reduces inner conflict that
reduces our self-deception and they're
not affords us to see more deeply into
reality and then that allows us right to
come to deeper more deeper contact with
reality the ability to come that ability
for realization is then internalized and
we realize better the nature of the
operations the patterns and processes in
her mind and our psyche she's more inner
harmony and then get that resonance you
get that reciprocal opening and it's
satisfying it's two of our deepest meta
desires our desire to be at peace with
ourselves to have a fullness of being
and a desire to come into contact with
this what is most real and that's
exactly right
the meditation practices where we're
getting that inner harmony that inner
awareness we're reducing into conflict
or offending ourselves and then in the
meta practice and then in the
integration practice right we're taking
an attention out in meta and with the
integration practice work wouldn't work
actually trying to realize these
patterns and processes in the world
harmonize resonate
more deeply realize remember the being
mode in our lives that resonates in and
we get exactly platonic yeah negau gay
but my use of platonic dialectic let
through the use of Buddhist and Taoist
meditative contemplative practices so
there is a deep convergence between
those two and I don't think that's going
to Temple so that's an excellent
question thank you for asking it by
connecting it to the Platonic framework
we get understanding of why we this
practice can be so good
precisely because it does address those
two deep fundamental drives the drives
that if these meta drives are not
satisfied everything else we do no
matter how successful will seem will be
undermined meta Drive of being at peace
with ourselves or friending ourselves in
the meta Drive of being in touch with
what is most real now why do us ask the
question do you have an insight into how
to apply today's lesson yesterday's
lesson when someone else lies Farms
Steel's etc that's a very hard question
um I'm struggling with somebody who is
extremely close to me who is actually
lying and not so much stealing but lying
and doing some self-destructive behavior
and I very deliberately in situation
where I was confronting them really
tried to come into the centering and
rooting I was doing that trying to open
up Metta as much as I can in the
practice and that was very very helpful
it's helpful you have to frame how it's
helpful it's helpful in getting you into
sort of the best adaptive orientation
and stance towards that person that
doesn't necessarily mean it is going to
be immediately causally effective or
easin evenly even ultimately effective
and you know changing them or reforming
them or helping them to get to realize
their line it increases the chance that
you will mirror back to them and help
them to be more reflective but it is no
guarantee because
that we don't have magical power over
the mystery of the complex dynamic
complexity of other human beings so it
helps but frame it in terms of what's
going on in the situation the reality
that you're confronting another human
being who is one of the most complex and
dynamically complex entities that you
will ever never encounter Austin Austin
Asst 97 I've experienced it when I
suspect when i sexually abstain my
mindfulness part this greatly deepens if
you have any knowledge of one so there's
two accounts I could give you and this
and I've done a little bit of practice
of Tantra to try and also understand as
I mentioned last time the the
interpenetration of mindfulness
practices and sexuality so there's two
answers from like a Western tradition
but in my mind I'm putting it into Vella
with what I've read and a little bit of
practice have done of Tantra right so
one of course is a second dynamic
approach and this is the idea that we
have sort of this don't know what to
call it actually in the metaphysics of
the secretary dynamic approach but you
know the Freudian Union idea of libido
we have sort of this basic energy of
attraction and motivation it's sort of
the continuity between our physiological
and metabolic energy and you know and
movement the the energetic movement of
our mind and our heart and then the idea
is when we sexually abstain that libido
gets reach annulled sublimated to use
the pro extra it gets reach annulled and
if that energy pours into something else
perhaps a particular practice now that's
interesting and I
and I I think it ties in it
psychodynamic stuff has got some very
powerful connections to the actual
phenomenology of our experience a more
cognitive perspective which has a lot
more sort of on the empirical evidence
and theoretical power going for it comes
from the work of Michael Anderson and
this is the idea of circuitry use or
excitation notice that my tongue
originally evolved for detecting poison
and moving food around my mouth effect
it's been cognitively appropriated
exacted for the cognitive function of
speech in the same way that circuitry of
care in that motivation and wanting to
be absorbed and coupled to and have a
participatory knowing of something that
we have in our sexuality can be exact
'add and put into write a deeper
absorption coupling and participatory
knowing of being and what is ultimately
most relevant and most real and those
two accounts I don't think are
inconsistent with each other you could
put them together and make sort of a
convergent argument that what we're
doing is exactly that kind of circuitry
use of redirecting the libido
this is perhaps in addition to the
social function of trying to protect
people from sexual predation this is
perhaps also why there has been
long-standing traditions of celibacy
associated with the spiritual practice
that being said it's not clear if
mandatory celibacy is good I'm not I'm
not recommending that I'm just trying to
explain why we see it showing up cross
culturally and cross historically I hope
that answers your question
Chris Trafford I've been following the
course since the beginning I'm
struggling with routing and finding my
flow
at first it was knowable and captured my
attention but now I find my mind water
and repeatedly and I struggled to find
greater depth or subtlety in the
sensations present that might continue
to arouse my interest I also find
visualization difficult I've never been
out to really feel rooted or to
visualize a route growing into the earth
yes so that is a difficulty there is why
variation within the population our
degree to which people can get absorbed
into visualization and so I want to be
responsive to your challenge Chris so
maybe to you know try doing a much more
later
looting not as deep and not just and
you're not going to get a lot of novelty
out of it remember we're not always
trying to recapture sort of a you know
strong intense experience just you know
do the core routing in the core of the
head right chest abdomen stomach let it
go flow just come into even a very basic
awareness and just you know just you're
just activating an integration of your
introspection looking into your mind
looking into your body with intercepts I
just feel you're out there and feel your
chest just kill it and then go in to the
practice and again don't worry so much
about the deep visualization perhaps if
you need to while you're doing the
routing practice actually just reach
touch the earth and just feel that
groundedness maybe for even say to
yourself I'm grounded I'm stable all
right and so perhaps that will help
sometimes when will people who have who
don't have a strong visualization more
external actions and a more compressed
form of doing this I can be helpful try
that and see if that's helpful
if not please come back and ask a
question again Andrey Ferreira
hello again Andrey I know that you said
that there are some bad ways of using
meditation I would just like to ask if
it's okay to use a quicksave in order to
solve an order to stall or meditate on
urges connected with addiction yes yes
that is not an abusive way so in any
ways in which we're addicted in any ways
in which we're following in to
reciprocal narrowing that one of the
uses of meditation of mindfulness is
exactly to allow us to confront and
challenge and respond to reciprocal
narrowing that we get in an addiction
and try and afford reciprocal opening so
is a completely appropriate thing to be
doing very very much so
max Breanna
are there any practices we can apply the
five precepts further through meditation
sometimes I consciously reflect on some
areas I like it so that that's
interesting so if you find that there's
an area you're lacking in one thing that
can sometimes work is let's say it's I'm
not I don't know you max I'm not
accusing you of anything let's say you
find that you're lying try to remember
the situation which you lied to somebody
pick it up in your mind and they do
Metta towards it do matter towards that
situation and try on Paul what was what
like what was happening in you what
identity are you assuming what's going
on and even apply the five factors of
acquiring mindfulness within there
within that site of matter what's going
on in the what identity I'm projecting
and the five factors been climbing
mindfulness with the matter on to the
person and really trying unpack what's
happening that situation for you social
green I was taught to minute with my
eyes open can you comment on the
benefits downside of eyes open or closed
so one of the benefits of eyes open is
that people are less likely to trigger a
lot of mental time travel zipping off
into the past it still happens but it's
reduced a bit one of the difficulties
with eyes open is it's much harder for
people to get the interoceptive stuff
get all the embodied awareness the sense
of flow so there's a bit of a trade-off
there I think that for novices overall
in my experience so this I don't have
scientific evidence is just anecdotal I
may be teaching this for a long time
generally novices find eyes closed
better than I slightly open
I hope that that answers your question
there is there is you know there is a
sense of strength and balances but it
seems like for novices eyes closed is a
better initial practice not mandatory of
course
I just recommend it for the reasons I
just gave you all right so thank you for
joining as always I want to thank my
dear friend and techno mage Omar and my
beloved son Jason please like this
stream that will increase its visibility
for the YouTube algorithm and that will
help other people to come to this
practice which is I think very helpful
at this time so in conjunction with that
please recommend this series perhaps my
channel to anybody you might find you
might think it might be helpful to
please subscribe to my channel that way
you'll get notification of new videos
and you'll get access to all of the
videos like for today I made reference
to video 5 awakening the meeting crisis
and the answer to one of the questions
so you can find a lot of resources there
for how to situate this practice into a
more encompassing transformation of your
life and cultivation of wisdom we're
doing this every weekday morning Monday
through Fridays Monday's Dharma day
Tuesday through Friday or six day we're
doing it every morning 9:30 est so
please remember continuity of practice
is ultimately more important than
quantity practice there is no enemy
worse to you than your own mind but
there is no ally friend greater to you
than your own money take care of
everyone I'll see you tomorrow